<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-30T10:12:18-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">VisionEval</title><subtitle>A common framework for strategic planning models.</subtitle><author><name>VisionEval</name></author><entry><title type="html">Links to interactive viewers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/interactive/2019/01/01/1-viewers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links to interactive viewers" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/interactive/2019/01/01/1-viewers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/interactive/2019/01/01/1-viewers.html">&lt;p&gt;A benefit of using strategic planning models is that they enable a large number of scenarios to be evaluated. This provides planners with more information about the potential consequences of future trends and the policies that might be put in place to influence those trends and their effects. This benefit also poses a challenge in regards to how to make sense of the large amounts of output data that are produced. Fortunately, the worldwide web and programming tools developed for programming web content assist with meeting the challenge and make it easier than ever to make model results available to planners and the public. Following are examples of model results visualizations that have been developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ve-rpat-scenario-viewer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://github.com/VisionEval/VisionEval/blob/master/sources/VEScenarioViewer/verpat.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VE-RPAT Scenario Viewer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows an exampple of the VE-RPAT Scenario Viewer, where the output from multiple VE-RPAT model runs can be viewed in an interactive fashion. The user can select different combinations of input factors and find out how various future outcomes are affected by each selection. Users can also select desired outcomes and find out what factors cause those outcomes to occur. By experimenting with the selections and observing the results, users will get a better understanding of the relationships between policy choices and context factors and future outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ve-rspm-scenario-viewer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://github.com/VisionEval/VisionEval/blob/master/sources/VEScenarioViewer/verspm.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VE-RSPM Scenario Viewer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows an example of the VE-RSPM Scenario Viewer, based on a similar structre to the VE-RPAT visualizer described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;odot-scenario-viewer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gregorbj.github.io/RSPM-Viewer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ODOT Scenario Viewer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ODOT’s scenario viewer is a web application that enables users to explore the results of modeling hundreds of scenarios in an interactive manner. Users can investigate how changing future assumptions affects outcome measures. They can also work backwards and determine what inputs are associated with outcomes they choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choices-and-voices&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dvrpc.org/choicesandvoices/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Choices and Voices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Delaware Valley Regional Planning Commission created a web application that allows the public to provide feedback on how the greater Philadelphia region should grow and how the transportation system for the region should be funded, managed, and improved. It provides feedback on how those choices affect various performance measures and allow users to submit their choices to planners.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VisionEval</name></author><category term="models" /><category term="enhancements" /><category term="viewers" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22so-simple-sample-image-4-narrow.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Links to additional resources</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/resources/2019/01/01/1-resources.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links to additional resources" /><published>2019-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/resources/2019/01/01/1-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/resources/2019/01/01/1-resources.html">&lt;p&gt;The rationale and design for the VisionEval framework are documented by papers included in the project’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gregorbj/VisionEval&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt; they include the following documents. Check the repository for the latest documents because the framework is still under development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;visioneval-strategic-tools-for-performance-based-planning&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/visioneval/VisionEval/wiki/documents/VisionEval_HandOut_2016PeerExchange.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VisionEval Strategic Tools for Performance-Based Planning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper provides an overview of VisionEval as a model system for implementing analysis tools to support long range performance-based planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;visioneval-a-new-framework-for-the-greenstep-family-of-models-overview-and-approach&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/visioneval/VisionEval/blob/master/api/rspm_framework_approach.md&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VisionEval: A New Framework for the GreenSTEP Family of Models: Overview and Approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper describes the rationale and project approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;visioneval-model-system-and-framework-design&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gregorbj/VisionEval/blob/master/api/model_system_design.md&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VisionEval Model System and Framework Design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper goes into more depth on how the framework fits into a model system and the design of that system and the framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tmip-webinar-introduction-to-greenstep-the-rspm-and-related-strategic-planning-models&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://connectdot.connectsolutions.com/p5rele3rf8o/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TMIP Webinar: Introduction to GreenSTEP, the RSPM and Related Strategic Planning Models.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a three-part webinar series on the GreenSTEP and RSPM models. This webinar focused on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The motivation for building the GreenSTEP model and the policy issues it was built to analyze.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design overview and major features.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other related models (EERPAT, RPAT) and their differences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GreenSTEP and RSPM application examples.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How the GreenSTEP and RSPM models are run.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to obtain the code and technical documentation for the GreenSTEP and RSPM models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tmip-webinar-design-and-estimation-of-the-greenstep-and-rspm-models&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://connectdot.connectsolutions.com/p4k5rg9luna/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TMIP Webinar: Design and Estimation of the GreenSTEP and RSPM Models.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second of a three-part webinar series on the GreenSTEP and RSPM models. This webinar focused on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrated model development process using R.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data and data preparation used in model development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of the household DVMT model.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of the light-weight vehicles model.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of the PHEV model.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of the household budget model.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of the congestion model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tmip-webinar-visioneval---a-modeling-system-for-building-strategic-planning-models&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://connectdot.connectsolutions.com/p52lbzs1qv0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TMIP Webinar: VisionEval - A Modeling System for Building Strategic Planning Models.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the third of a three-part webinar series on the GreenSTEP and RSPM models. This webinar focused on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The reasons for creating VisionEval.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Model system objectives.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overview of the model system architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Key principles that enable ‘plug-and-play’ operation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Module structure and the packaging of modules.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What happens behind the scenes when a model runs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to download and use the code.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>VisionEval</name></author><category term="models" /><category term="resources" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22so-simple-sample-image-4-narrow.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ongoing work for all tools</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/1-ongoing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ongoing work for all tools" /><published>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/1-ongoing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/1-ongoing.html">&lt;p&gt;The ongoing work involves:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outstanding work on the migration of RSPM, RPAT, and GreenSTEP to the VisionEval framework is outlined in the GitHub wiki’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/VisionEval/VisionEval/wiki/Modules-and-Packages&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Modules &amp;amp; Packages&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/visioneval/VisionEval/wiki/Development-Roadmap&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/a&gt; pages. Now that these are in a common framework, future enhancements of any tool should be usable by all other tools. For example, a module which captures multi-modal travel in VE-RSPM can also be used with VE-RPAT, as both models will use similar structures and share code.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Updated Multi-Modal travel modules were built by PSU for VE-RSPM through a peer-reviewed ODOT Research project (completed in June 2017).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a pilot contributor &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/VisionEval/VisionEval/wiki/Review-Team-Charter&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Review Team&lt;/a&gt; effort completed in September 2017, a review team of agency partner, academic, and consultants reviewed industry code governance best practices, developed a VisionEval charter and review process, and piloted this process using the Multi-Modal travel modules as a test case code submittal for inclusion in the VisionEval repository.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/VisionEval/VisionEval/wiki/Documentation-Plan&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Documentation Plan&lt;/a&gt; has been developed to describe what is needed to produce comprehensive documentation at multiple levels of detail.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/VisionEval/VisionEval/wiki/VE-State-Status&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VE-State&lt;/a&gt;, a state-level version of VE-RSPM to replicate the functionality of GreenSTEP, was completed in 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-enhancements&quot;&gt;Future Enhancements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VERSPM will be extended with additional modules via the Pooled Fund. These future enhancements are planned to be carried out in a way which can be used for RPAT and GreenSTEP as well as RSPM.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A wish list of desired upgrades, reflecting agency partner priorities per an August 2016 Peer Exchange in Portland, is available at the GitHub &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/visioneval/VisionEval/wiki/Development-Roadmap&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to new tool functionality, possible future enhancements might also include scenario planning support, such as case studies, reasonable ranges of various policy inputs, aids to facilitate transit and land use inputs, equity analyses, and peer review of VisionEval tools.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VisionEval</name></author><category term="models" /><category term="enhancements" /><summary type="html">as listed on the Development Roadmap</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22so-simple-sample-image-4-narrow.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Regional Strategic Planning Model (RSPM) &amp;amp; Scenario Viewer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/3-rspm.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Regional Strategic Planning Model (RSPM) &amp; Scenario Viewer" /><published>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/3-rspm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/3-rspm.html">&lt;p&gt;The Regional Strategic Planning Model (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oregon.gov/ODOT/Planning/Documents/RSPM-Quick-Summary.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RSPM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) was developed by ODOT as an offshoot of the GreenSTEP model to support metropolitan area scenario planning projects. The name reflects a broadening of the outcomes and policies for local agency use. Outcomes beyond GHG emissions requirements, such as non-motorized travel are emphasized with a focus on the types of policies and investment actions that are often implemented at the regional or local jurisdiction level. The essential steps of RSPM are similar to GreenSTEP, with a crucial difference of geographic scale. RSPM subdivides metropolitan areas into districts, which are similar to census tracts, and groups of districts, as divisions, to represent the separate policy actions of jurisdictions within the metropolitan area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interactive viewer of previously run results from hundreds or thousands of scenarios was added to RSPM.  The viewer enables learning about the impact and tradeoffs of different policy combinations, resilience under a range of conditions, and can help to catch inconsistent thinking where residents support a broad community goal but discard the specific actions available to reach it. To date, several agencies have built web-based interactive viewers around scenarios run from VisionEval tools, allowing users a way to explore the effects of various choices for their region’s future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-status&quot;&gt;Current Status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RSPM model, along with a graphical user interface and output scenario viewer (similar to RSPM viewer) was transferred to the common VisionEval framework.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VisionEval</name></author><category term="models" /><summary type="html">Overview</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22so-simple-sample-image-4-narrow.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GreenSTEP</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/4-greenstep.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GreenSTEP" /><published>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/4-greenstep</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/4-greenstep.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oregon.gov/ODOT/Planning/Documents/GreenSTEP-Model-Overview.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GreenSTEP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was the first of these models to be developed, and was designed by the Oregon Department of Transportation (ODOT) to assist in the development of plans to reduce greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions from light-duty vehicles to meet statutory goals. GreenSTEP models the consequences of changes in many different factors (such as transportation supply, prices, and land use) on household vehicle ownership and use, and the resulting effects on emissions, traffic congestion, and other outcomes. It’s strength is in the ability to incorporate significant detail through modeling a synthetic set of individual households and associated vehicles and fuels, incorporating a budget model for pricing policies, while avoiding network details that lead to long run times.  GreenSTEP, a statewide model with county and metro area “zones”, has been used to establish long-range goals and identify the possible strategies to achieve these goals, such as reducing transportation related emissions by a certain percent, or ensuring that a certain percent of households live in walkable neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design concepts in GreenSTEP are the cornerstone of the related models. As a strategic planning model, GreenSTEP sits between sketch planning models that operate using simplified rule-based methods use, and modeling each individual’s daily trips by purpose on a detailed network with interacting policies. . GreenSTEP and the other VisionEval models simulate individual households and interactions between policies, but forecasts only overall travel based on metropolitan-wide travel conditions rather than detailed networks, striking a balance between rapid computation of alternative scenarios and accurate representations of how different types of households will change travel behavior in response to policies and investments. These models allow rapid analysis of how actions may interact, such as how urban area density may interact with electric vehicle ownership or car sharing. They can also test how household behavior may respond to policy changes, for instance how VMT may change in response to future increases in fuel cost or tighter budgets during stagnant economic times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inputs to GreenSTEP are similar to what is required for the other VisionEval models. These can be summarized into household characteristics (age mix, household size, personal income, dwelling type), vehicle characteristics (fuel economy, vehicle age, powertrain type), and place characteristics (density, amount of transit service, mixed use development). Given these attributes, the model estimates outputs such as household travel, travel costs, emissions, and road congestion and environmental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-status&quot;&gt;Current Status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GreenSTEP continues to be used as a State-wide planning tool by ODOT, but is not available on a public repository currently. The FHWA maintains the similar statewide Energy and Emissions Reduction Policy Analysis Tool (EERPAT) model.  EERPAT has just made a significant enhancement to add a freight model and associated policies built on FHWA Freight Analysis Framework commodity flow data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The models developed from GreenSTEP form the core of all VisionEval models. Following the successful transfer of RSPM and RPAT to the VisionEval project, a pilot statewide VisionEval model has also been transferred to the framework, as an extension of RSPM. This effort was led by Oregon DOT (and Maryland DOT) , via a contract led by CH2M Hill with sub-consultants RSG, Inc. and the original GreenSTEP author of Oregon Systems Analytics. It is currently being tested. This should greatly facilitate transferring EERPAT to VisionEval.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VisionEval</name></author><category term="models" /><summary type="html">Overview</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22so-simple-sample-image-4-narrow.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Rapid Policy Analysis Tool (RPAT)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/2-rpat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rapid Policy Analysis Tool (RPAT)" /><published>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/2-rpat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/users/2018/01/01/2-rpat.html">&lt;p&gt;The Rapid Policy Analysis Tool (&lt;a href=&quot;https://planningtools.transportation.org/551/rapid-policy-analysis-tool.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RPAT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) was developed under the federal Strategic Highway Research Program (SHRP2). The model was developed to help planners evaluate the potential effect of growth policies on regional travel. Portions of the GreenSTEP model were used in RPAT, but substantial revisions were made to the code, including use of land use place type categories representing the built environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like RSPM, RPAT is built off of the GreenSTEP code for evaluating effects of scenarios at the household level, and operates on a single metropolitan region geographical level, disaggregated by land use place type. An additional distinction between RSPM and RPAT is the type of policies that are intended to be tested, and the data requirements to set up the model. RPAT is focused on smart growth and land use planning, and aims to identify the most promising polices to achieve smart growth targets. RPAT can evaluate policies which affect changes to the built environment (such as transit-oriented development and proportion of population in mixed-use areas), changes to travel demand (such as development near the urban core and changes in firm size and industry), changes in transportation supply (such as amount of regional transit service), and changes in policies (such as intelligent transportation system strategies and demand management). RPAT produces safety performance measures in addition to other travel and environmental results of RSPM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-status&quot;&gt;Current Status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A VisionEval version of RPAT is under design. Following the completion of the transition of RSPM to the VisionEval framework, RPAT will be transitioned as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>VisionEval</name></author><category term="models" /><summary type="html">- Overview</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/%7B%22feature%22=%3E%22so-simple-sample-image-4-narrow.jpg%22,%20%22credit%22=%3Enil,%20%22creditlink%22=%3Enil%7D" /></entry></feed>